Finding Aid for Gunnar Birkerts and Associates, 1960-2014
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Gunnar Birkerts and Associates records 1960-2014
Gunnar Birkerts & Associates.
10000 drawings
87 linear feet of records
Architectural firm founded by Gunnar Birkerts, headquartered in Bloomfield Hills, Michigan. Textual records, architectural and engineering drawings and photographs document fourteen of the firm's major buildings including the Federal Reserve Building (Minneapolis, MN), Corning Glass Museum (Corning, NY) and the University of Michigan Law School Library Addition.
9915 Bb 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group was donated by Gunnar Birkerts (donor # 8285 ) in July, 1994. Subsequent accessions have been received.
The collection is open for research.
Gunnar Birkerts is an internationally acclaimed architect of the last half of the twentieth century who has been recognized for his expressive forms, his simplification of detail, his innovative work with surface materials and his effective use of indirect daylight. With his design flexibility and commitment to "finding poetry in building technology," he has pushed beyond the boundaries of the Modern Movement. [1]
Born on January 17, 1925, in Riga, Latvia, Gunnar Birkerts' childhood was steeped in the mythology of his country, as both of his parents, Peteris and Merija Shop Birkerts, were scholars and folklorists who studied the cultural heritage of the Latvian people. Later in his career, Birkerts expressed his gratitude for the rich, architectural and literary images of his homeland which he believed continued to stimulate his creative process.
While attending the first gymnasium in Riga, Birkerts saw an architectural rendering of an upperclassman which inspired him at the age of thirteen to pursue a career in this field. He completed two degrees in engineering and architecture in 1949 at the Technische Hochschule in Stuttgart, where his training exposed him to both Bauhaus and vernacular design. His education in the craft and technology program gave him an understanding of architectural materials and design construction methodology, which would become enduring interests throughout his career.
During his training, Gunnar Birkerts studied the work of Alvar Aalto, Gunnar Asplund, Sven Markelius and Sigurd Lewerentz in Europe and that of Mies van der Rohe, Walter Gropius, Erich Mendelsohn and Marcel Breuer, who had emigrated to the United States. William Lescaze and Frank Lloyd Wright were also of interest to him. However, it was at the U.S. Information Agency Library that he discovered and became attracted to the modern architecture of Eliel and Eero Saarinen with whom he shared northern European roots. Thus, he came to Birmingham, Michigan in December 1949 to seek work with Eero Saarinen, who explained to him upon his arrival in Birmingham, Michigan, that the General Motors Technical Center project was on hold and that no job was available for him. Carrying a letter of recommendation from Saarinen, Birkerts went to Chicago to join the firm of Perkins and Will, which specialized in school architecture. Within a year of his arrival in the United States, he married Sylvia Zvirbulis. Together they had three children, Sven Peter, Andra Sylvia and Erik Gunnar, born in 1951, 1954 and 1967, respectively.
In 1951, Eero Saarinen invited Birkerts to join his firm in Birmingham, Michigan, where he worked with such young architects as Kevin Roche, Robert Venturi and John Dinkeloo. During his four years with Saarinen, he contributed to the General Motors Technical Center in Warren, Michigan and Concordia Senior College in Fort Wayne, Indiana and was the project architect for the Milwaukee County War Memorial. In 1954, he won the young Designer of the Year Award from the Akron Museum of Art. Birkerts was highly impressed by Saarinen's inventiveness and perseverance, qualities which he carried into his own work. He recalls that "in those days it was a battle to bring modern architecture to the world. The whole quest was evangelistic." [2]
Birkerts received American citizenship in 1955, shortly after leaving Saarinen's office to join Donald Grieb in Milwaukee. After one year with Grieb, he was invited by Minoru Yamasaki to work with Yamasaki, Leinweber and Associates, in Birmingham, Michigan. There he was chief designer for the Reynolds Metals Building, the Educational Building at Wayne State University and the Daharan Air Terminal between 1956 and 1959. During this time, he received a number of design awards, including two citations from Progressive Architecture for houses in Wisconsin and first prize in the Cantu, Italy First International Furniture Competition. He was especially proud of the latter because Alvar Aalto, highly esteemed by Birkerts, was one of the jurists.
In 1959, Birkerts became a principal of Minoru Yamasaki and Associates. Despite his admiration for Yamasaki's intuitive creation process, Birkerts thought, "I had listened long enough. My apprenticeship was over. Now it was my turn to speak." [3] Accordingly, he left Yamasaki in 1959 to establish the partnership of Birkerts and Straub. With Frank Straub as project administrator and Birkerts as designer, they produced their first independent projects, including the Schwartz Summer Residence (1960-1962) in Northville, Michigan, the Haley Funeral Home (1960-1961) in Southfield, Michigan, the 1300 Lafayette East Apartments (1961-1963) in Detroit, the Marathon Oil Office Building (1962-1964) in Detroit and the Lillibridge Elementary School Addition (1962-1963) in Detroit.
Birkerts began his twenty-nine-year teaching career at the University of Michigan at this time as well. In 1961, he was appointed assistant professor of architecture, becoming associate professor of architecture in 1963 and professor of architecture in 1969. He was awarded the position of professor emeritus in 1990.
Gunnar Birkerts and Associates was established in 1963 in Birmingham, Michigan, when the architect left his partnership with Frank Straub. The 1960s were prolific years for the practice, as Birkerts designed buildings which contained the "bold forms, space before structure, minimal detailing, stratified walls and daylight in interior spaces" which were the hallmarks of his work during this decade.[4] Among his many important buildings of this period were the University Reformed Church (1960-1964) in Ann Arbor, Michigan, the Detroit Institute of Arts - South Wing Addition (1964), the Fisher Administrative Center (1964-1966) at the University of Detroit, the Lincoln Elementary School (1965-1967) in Columbus, Indiana, the Freeman Residence (1964-1966) in Grand Rapids, Michigan, the Tougaloo College Campus Master Plan (1965) in Tougaloo, Mississippi, the Tougaloo College Dormitories and Library (1966-1972) and the Federal Reserve Bank of Minneapolis (1967-1973).
During the 1970s, Birkerts continued his exploration of glass and metal as surface technologies. He was also an early advocate for the containment of urban sprawl with his Subterranean Urban Systems Study of 1974, for which he received a Fellowship Grant from the Graham Foundation for Advanced Studies in the Fine Arts. In 1970, he was elected a Fellow of the American Institute of Architects, and he received a Gold Medal from the American Institute of Architects, Detroit, in 1975. He was also honored by an appointment as Architect in Residence at the American Academy in Rome in 1976. A few of his many notable buildings of this decade are the Contemporary Arts Museum (1970-1972) in Houston, the Dance Instructional Facility (1970-1976) at the State University of New York, Purchase, the University of Michigan Law School Addition (1974-1981) in Ann Arbor, the United States Embassy Office Building (1975, project) in Helsinki, Finland, the Duluth Public Library (1969-1980), the Museum of Glass (1976-1980) in Corning, New York, and the University of Iowa College of Law Building (1979-1986) in Iowa City.
Birkerts received many more awards in the 1980s and 1990s, including the Arnold W. Brunner Memorial Prize in Architecture from The American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters (1981) and the first Bruce Alonzo Goff Professorship of Creative Architecture (1990) at the University of Oklahoma. In a poll conducted by The Buildings Journal of 58 architecture academicians in 1982, Gunnar Birkerts was listed as one of the top ten architects of non-residential structures in the nation, along with I. M. Pei, Romaldo Giurgola, Cesar Pelli, Kevin Roche, Philip Johnson, Michael Graves, Charles Moore, Edward Larrabee Barnes and Richard Meier. Among his important buildings of this period are the Ferguson Residence (1980-1983) in Kalamazoo, Michigan, the Cornell University Uris Library Addition (1980-1982) in Ithaca, New York, the Conservatory of Music Library Addition (1986-1988) in Oberlin, Ohio, and the United States Embassy Office Building (1987-89) in Caracas, Venezuela.
In 1997, Birkerts dissolved Gunnar Birkerts and Associates. He is continuing his practice of architecture from his studio in Bloomfield Hills. Now in the fifth decade of his prolific career, Birkerts is designing the Joint Library of the City of San Jose and San Jose State University in California, the first institution in the country to combine the repositories of a university and a city under one roof. Such other recent works as the Ohio State University College of Law Addition (1988-1993) in Columbus, the Kemper Museum of Contemporary Art and Design (1991-1994) of the Kansas City Art Institute, and the National Library (1989 - in progress) in Riga, Latvia are testament to the innovation, monumentality and freedom of Birkerts' "expressive architecture."[5] The National Library exemplifies Birkerts' powerful use of metaphor which has characterized his work throughout his career and has made his buildings among the most distinctive of the twentieth century.
______________________________
Notes
[1]
Gunnar Birkerts Gunnar Birkerts: Process and Expression in Architectural Form (Norman: University of Oklahoma Press,1994), 32.
[2]
Robert Benson, "An Interview with Gunnar Birkerts," Inland Architect (Jan./Feb.1986): 31.
[3]
Kay Kaiser The Architecture of Gunnar Birkerts (Washington, D.C.: The American Institute of Architects Press, 1989), 13.
[4]
Ibid., 15.
[5]
Kay Kaiser, "World Architecture Profile: Gunnar Birkerts," Global Architecture, 36:26.
The Gunnar Birkerts and Associates Collection offers researchers a rich perspective on the work of one of the masters of American modern architecture whose career spans the second half of the twentieth century and into the twenty-first. The initial accessions of Birkert's material encompassed 69 linear feet of the firm's textual records, which are associated with 14 of Birkerts' distinguished buildings, and 7158 original drawings and prints documenting the evolution of the architectural design process for each project. In 2008, the records and drawings of 74 more projects were included in the collection, bringing the total amount of textual material to 82 linear feet and the number of drawings to over 10,000. Altogether, these visual materials detail many of the expressive elements for which Birkerts' architecture is renowned, including his bold forms, simplification of detail, innovative selection of surface materials and dramatic use of indirect light. Although six of the buildings in the original collection of 14 projects are located in Michigan, along with the offices of the firm, nine other structures were built in New York, Indiana, Mississippi and Minnesota, testimony to the national scope of this architectural practice. The following buildings were selected for inclusion in the collection by Birkerts and Bentley Historical Library staff because they represent the significance, diversity and evolution of the architect's work:
Haley Funeral Home (1960-1961)
University Reformed Church (1960-1964)
Freeman Residence (1964-1966)
Lincoln Elementary School (1965-1967)
Tougaloo College Master Plan, Library and Dormitories (1965-1972)
Federal Reserve Bank of Minneapolis (1967-1973)
Duluth Public Library (1969-1980)
S.U.N.Y., Purchase, Dance Instructional Facility (1970-1976)
Corning Municipal Fire Station (1973-1974)
Calvary Baptist Church (1974-1977)
University of Michigan Law Library Addition (1974-1981)
Corning Museum of Glass (1976-1980)
Ferguson Residence (1980-1983)
St. Peter's Lutheran church (1981-1988)
Additional Projects (added in 2008)
The initial accessions Gunnar Birkerts and Associates Collection are arranged in 14 series, each of which contains the business records and architectural drawings for one building. The finding aid begins with a description of the narrative records in chronological order in each series. An item-level description of the architectural and engineering drawings follows, grouping drawings in folders according to design phases, as described above. The finding aid lists the titles of drawings, when they exist, as well as title bar information including original dates, revision dates, numeric sequencing and, in some cases, names of consulting engineers. A description of the medium and support of each drawing is also given.
The 2008 accession to the collection includes of documentation of 74 additional projects consisting of 3,000 drawings and 13 linear feet of textual materials and photographs. The documentation for these projects is generally not as extensive as for the fourteen in the original accessions and the finding aid does not describe them in as great detail. They have been grouped together as single series titled "Other Projects" and the individual projects are listed in alphabetical order by project title
One of the collection's greatest strengths is found in its emphasis on the architectural design process, offering researchers a broad, visual representation of the evolution of each building through the "Schematic Design," "Design Development" and "Construction Document" sequences. Because Gunnar Birkerts and Associates meticulously saved each drawing associated with the firm's projects, this collection provides an exceptional view of the daily design process, as solutions were sought which defined the architectural character and individuality of a structure. Each of the 14 buildings in the Gunnar Birkerts and Associates Collection is conceived as an individual series, which contains the textual and visual documents associated with the project. Within each of the 14 series, the architectural and engineering drawings are arranged chronologically by design phase, beginning with "Schematic Design," when the owner's program is analyzed and sketches are drawn to illustrate the scale and relationship of the project's components. Researchers interested in viewing the earliest conceptual drawings associated with each building are encouraged to consult the finding aid of the collateral Gunnar Birkerts Collection, which amasses the sketches by the architect's own hand for most of his projects. Digital images of 284 of these conceptual sketches can be seen online in the Bentley Historical Library Image Bank through Gunnar Birkerts, Conceptual Drawings. An understanding of the beginning stage of design for each building is best obtained by studying the conceptual and "Schematic Design" documents in both the Gunnar Birkerts and Associates Collection and the Gunnar Birkerts Collection.
The second "Design Development" stage in each building series includes more precise site plans, floor plans, elevations and sections which further define the dimensions, mechanical/electrical systems, building materials and architectural character of the project. This phase often ends with the production of artistic presentation drawings which are used to obtain the client's approval of the design. Although the collection contains a large majority of original sketches and drawings on tracing paper, vellum, linen and mylar, many blue-line and sepia prints have been retained in each series if they are substitutes for missing originals or if they are annotated and thus show the ongoing search for solutions in the evolution of the design process.
Each series in the collection also records the third "Construction Document" phase, during which the final working drawings are developed before being sent to contractors for bids. These drawings are the graphic representation of the written "Specifications," included in the textual records of every series. The "Construction Documents" for each building, which were often revised to show changes after construction began, may be of significant value to historic preservationists or future owners seeking to restore the building to its original condition or adapt it to a new use.
The Gunnar Birkerts and Associates Collection is also significant in its pairing of the visual documentation described above with the textual records of each building, which describe the decisions and actions of the firm during the design and construction process. Thus, scholars can read the program information, specifications, addenda and memoranda associated with the architectural drawings during each chronological stage of the building's design. Written contracts, correspondence, transmittals and field inspection reports further inform historians about the relationship between the firm and its clients, contractors, consulting engineers, landscape architects and sub-contractors, documenting in rich detail the business affairs of a nationally known architectural firm in the second half of the twentieth century. Of particular value within the narrative records of each building series is the "Architect's Conceptual Statement". These statements offer design and history students an opportunity to understand the interchange of objective and subjective influences on Mr. Birkerts' creative process and the solutions which define the architectural character of each building.
The Gunnar Birkerts and Associates Collection is also of exceptional value to scholars because it represents the end of the era of hand-drawn architectural documents. By the end of the twentieth century, many architects have begun to use the computer in the development of design and construction drawings. However, this collection of the original 14 buildings contains only drawings which show the flow of the creative process from the brain, through the hand, to the paper. Even drawings which are marked "void" are retained because, like annotated prints, they show the evolution of the design as the search for architectural solutions begins to define the building. Whereas the use of computer-aided design would undoubtedly delete many intermediary design drawings from a collection, this aggregation of hand-drawn documents shows the artistry and complexity of the creative process. The beauty of the architect's pencil line on delicate tracing paper, smooth vellum and opaque mylar is preserved here for future generations of scholars, just as its use in the late 1990s is being abandoned by many architects.
In 2015, Gunnar Birkerts donated a large collection of 7,840 color 35 mm slides, associated with the design and construction of 123 projects, documenting through photographs the work of his entire career. This additional collection is encompassed in the series titled, "Photographic Slides of Projects."
Subjects:
Architectural design.; Architectural firms--Michigan.; Architectural practice--Michigan.; Architecture--Designs and plans--Presentation drawings.; Architecture--Designs and plans--Working drawings.; Architecture, Domestic--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Architecture, Domestic--Michigan--Kalamazoo.; Architecture--Michigan.; Architecture, Modern.; Bank buildings--Minnesota--Minneapolis.; Barnes, Edward Larrabee, 1915-2004; Birkerts, Gunnar.; Birkerts and Straub.; Calvary Baptist Church (Detroit, Mich.); Church architecture--Indiana--Columbus.; Church architecture--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Church architecture--Michigan--Detroit.; Corning Municipal Fire Station (Corning, N.Y.); Corning Museum of Glass.; Dance Instructional Facility (State University of New York College at Purchase); Duluth Public Library.; Federal Reserve Bank of Minneapolis.; Ferguson Residence (Kalamazoo, Mich.); Fire stations--New York--Corning.; Freeman Residence (Grand Rapids, Mich.); Funeral homes--Michigan--Southfield.; Gunnar Birkerts & Associates.; Haley Funeral Home (Southfield, Mich.); Law Library Addition (University of Michigan); Library architecture--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Light in architecture.; Lincoln Elementary School (Columbus, Ind.); Museum buildings--New York.; St. Peter's Lutheran Church (Columbus, Ind.); School buildings--Indiana--Columbus.; Tougaloo College.; Underground architecture--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Law Library.; University Reformed Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Material:
Banks--Minnesota--Minneapolis.; Churches--Indiana--Columbus.; Construction.; Corning Municipal Fire Station (Corning, N.Y.); Corning Museum of Glass.; Dance Instructional Facility (State University of New York College at Purchase); Duluth Public Library.; Dwellings--Michigan--Kalamazoo.; Federal Reserve Bank of Minneapolis.; Ferguson Residence (Kalamazoo, Mich.); Fire stations--New York--Corning.; Galleries & museums--New York--Corning.; Gunnar Birkerts & Associates.; Law Library Addition (University of Michigan); Libraries--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Libraries--Minnesota--Duluth.; Lincoln Elementary School (Columbus, Ind.); Schools--Indiana--Columbus.; St. Peter's Lutheran Church (Columbus, Ind.); Tougaloo College.; Universities & colleges--Mississippi--Tougaloo.; Universities & colleges--New York--Purchase.
Contributors:
Bartholomew Consolidated School Corporation (Columbus, Ind.); Charles Wood Associates.; Darvas, Robert M.; E.G. Siegel Associates.; Herbert Kunstadt Associates.; Holforty, Clifford W.; Holforty, Widrig, O'Neill & Levin Associates.; Hoyem Associates.; Hoyem, Basso and Adams.; Hoyem, Basso, Adams and Martin.; Hoyem-Basso Associates.; John Grissim and Associates.; Johnson, Johnson & Roy.; Jaros, Baum & Bolles.; Joseph R. Loring and Associates.; LeMessurier Associates.; Paul H. Seiz Associates.; Peter G. Rollard and Associates.; Potapa Mancini and Associates.; Robert M. Darvas Associates.; Sasaki Associates.; Skilling, Helle, Christiansen, Robertson.; Smith and Sanders.; Syska & Hennessy.
Genre/Form:
Architectural drawings.; Architectural & site components.; Architectural photographs.; Photographs.; Progress photographs.
- Haley Funeral Home, Southfield, Michigan 1960-1985, 38 drawings; 0.1 linear feet
  Architect: Birkerts and Straub
  Structural Engineer: Clifford W. Holforty, P.E.
  Contractor: Walter H. Desimpel Company
  Earliest Dated Drawing: April 15, 1960
  Latest Dated Drawing: June 2, 1974